Order of operations is most prevalent in arithmetic,
and, as a result, many logic errors, meaning
errors in intended calculations, occur with
arithmetic.
Before we look at a code example, let’s
ensure we understand the order of operations
related to arithmetic.
The order is as follows:
Parentheses
Exponents
Multiplication
Division, including Modulus, which is a remainder
after division
Addition
Subtraction
A common mnemonic used to remember the order
of operations is Please Excuse My Dear Aunt
Sally for Parentheses, Exponents, Multiplication,
Division, Addition, and Subtraction.
It is very important to ensure we understand
the order of operations to avoid logic problems
in any calculations within our apps.
Let’s look at examples of how the order
of operations works with arithmetic.
Here is a code example, 134-arithmetic, where
the total score should be the base score plus
the bonus amount, with that total multiplied
by a person’s rank within a game.
That formula is on line 5.
We are looking for a total score of 13,500
on paper, as the base plus the bonus is 4500,
and the rank is 3.
But let’s run this code and see what the
result is, as the calculation is currently
built.
The result is only 5500, not 13,500.
In a game situation, a player would not be
happy with a much lower score than what is
expected.
Let’s apply the order of operations to the
formula on line 5.
The perceived problem with this formula is
the assumption that math always occurs left
to right.
In this case, one might think that the base
is added to the bonus, totaling 4500, and
then multiplied by the rank, 3, to get to
13500.
In arithmetic, the order of operations dictates
that multiplication occurs before addition.
Thus, the bonus is multiplied by the rank
first, giving us 1500, and then added to the
base score, 4000, giving us the 5500 result
we see.
How do we fix the formula, then?
Do you remember what the first priority is
in the order of operations?
If you said parentheses, you are correct.
We want the score to be calculated first,
so I will put parentheses around base plus
bonus.
That part of the score will calculate first
and then multiply by the rank to get the total
score.
Let’s rerun the code.
The formula now works as intended.
A good practice with any formula with multiple
operators is to figure out what must be done
first and put that part of the code in parentheses,
even if the parentheses are unnecessary.
We want to convey to others the top priorities
within a calculation.
Finally, compared to the other operator types
we have covered so far: assignment, comparison,
and logical, arithmetic takes priority.
Why?
Think of it this way: if we had two calculations
to compare to see if one is greater than the
other, wouldn’t we need to do the calculations
first?
We would, and that’s why arithmetic is the
top priority among the different types of
operators used in Python and other programming
languages.